Finding Aid for Mosaic Club (Jackson, Mich.) records, 1886-1962
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Mosaic Club (Jackson, Mich.) records 1886-1962
Mosaic Club (Jackson, Mich.).
2 linear feet
2010014 Bk
Jackson, Michigan, women’s organization devoted to the mental improvement of its members through lectures and presentations; minutes of club meetings, yearbooks and programs, scrapbooks and miscellaneous other records.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was transferred from the William Clements Library in 2009 (donor no. 1333 ).
No further additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
The Mosaic Club of Jackson, Michigan was established in 1886 to provide its members with the opportunity to broaden their knowledge through shared study and thought. Topics for study, assigned to specific members three weeks prior to meetings, included a variety of subjects, for example, literature and history of Rome, famous cathedrals, conservation. Individual programs were created for each meeting, where members presented their findings in the form of lectures and readings.
The original by-laws allowed for thirty-five members, which included four officers; president, vice-president, secretary, and treasure. Each member paid an initiation fee of $25, and yearly dues of $1.00. Yearbooks included the topics to be studied and the members assigned to present the results of their study at club meetings.
From 1886 to 1962 the club met twenty times per year on Tuesday at the homes of the members.
The records of the Mosaic Club of Jackson, Michigan reflect the activities and interests typical of women's clubs in the late 19th and early 20th century. The record group has been arranged in into the following series: Minutes; Yearbooks and Programs; and Other Records.
Subjects:
Jackson (Mich.); Mosaic Club (Jackson, Mich.); Women--Michigan--Jackson--Societies, etc.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Minutes
  Nine volumes of club meeting Minutes, covering several periods of operation from 1886 through 1957, provide a record of club functions and administration.
  - 1886-1889 (Box 1)
  - 1890-1892, 2 volumes in 1 folder (Box 1)
  - March 1892-May 1892 (Box 1)
  - 1899-1905 (Box 1)
  - 1907-1910 (Box 1)
  - 1910-1914 (Box 1)
  - 1914-1917 (Box 1)
  - 1931-1937 (Box 1)
  - 1945-1957 (Box 1)
- Yearbooks and Programs
  Yearbooks and Programs contains the majority of the yearbooks created during the history of the Club, with gaps in the later years of the clubs existence, as well as some of the individual programs created for club meetings.
  - Yearbooks, 1986-1962 (Box 1)
  - Programs, ca. 1888-1911 (scattered) (Box 1)
  - Album entitled "Complete file of Mosaic Club programs from 1886 to date," 1886-1923 (Box 2)
    (includes both yearbooks and programs, and other miscellanea)
  - Album containing photographs, yearbooks, newspaper clippings, ca. 1920-1953 (Box 2)
- Other Records
  Other Records contains bylaws, miscellaneous correspondence, newspaper clippings, photographs, and other papers related to club operations.
  - Anniversary album, 1893 containing portraits and accounts of meetings (Box 2)
    (also later photographs from the 1920s)
  - Volume containing readings, poetry, and other toasts given on President's Day, March 27, 1932 (Box 2)
  - By-laws, 1893, 1897, 1933 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1889-1962 (Box 2)
  - Clippings, ca. 1890-1942 (Box 2)
  - Other papers, ca. 1888-1912 (Box 2)
    (includes treasurers report, memorial booklet, member list, etc.)
  - Photographs of members at meetings and some individual portraits, 1889-1931 (Box 2)